<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Vishnu Deva</title>
        <link>https://krvdev.com/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Vishnu Deva</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:08:18 +0530</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://krvdev.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>My First Post</title>
            <link>https://krvdev.com/posts/my-first-post/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:08:18 +0530</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://krvdev.com/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
            <description>Just a trial of Hugo. Pretty promising so far. Here&amp;rsquo;s another try.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a trial of Hugo. Pretty promising so far. Here&rsquo;s another try.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Automating AMI Creation</title>
            <link>https://krvdev.com/posts/ami-creation-automation/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://krvdev.com/posts/ami-creation-automation/</guid>
            <description>This document briefly delves into Hashicorp Packer and what it can do for your AWS AMI creation workflow.
Setting up an AMI in the usual way is a well-defined sequence of steps:
Create an instance from an existing AMI, private or public.
SSH into the instance.
Execute a series of commands to configure it.
Stop the instance.
Create an AMI.
Terminate the instance.
If you need the AMI in a different region or account, do that manually from the console.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This document briefly delves into Hashicorp Packer and what it can do for your AWS AMI creation workflow.</p>
<p>Setting up an AMI in the usual way is a well-defined sequence of steps:</p>
<p>Create an instance from an existing AMI, private or public.</p>
<p>SSH into the instance.</p>
<p>Execute a series of commands to configure it.</p>
<p>Stop the instance.</p>
<p>Create an AMI.</p>
<p>Terminate the instance.</p>
<p>If you need the AMI in a different region or account, do that manually from the console.</p>
<p>Repeat steps 1-7 whenever you need a change in the AMI.</p>
<p>Since AMI creation is such an involved and lengthy process, we might sometimes prefer to have an installation script that runs every time an instance is launched with the AMI and have the script configure the instance to suit our needs. This renders the launched instance unusable for a period of time until the installation is complete. Justifiably, this cost might be acceptable as opposed to the alternative of following the lengthy workflow laid out above every time you need your AMI updated with a new package.</p>
<p>But what if we could automate this process and treat AMI creation like a git push or a simple configuration change?</p>
<p>Enter Packer.</p>
<p>Packer automates every step in the AMI creation workflow using a JSON template that you define, which means that your workflow for setting up an AMI will now look like this:</p>
<p>Create a JSON template for Packer to create your AMI.</p>
<p>packer validate template.json</p>
<p>packer build template.json</p>
<p>When you need to update the AMI, modify your template to make the changes you need, and run step 2.</p>
<p>Example Use Case</p>
<p>You need to build an AMI with the following properties:</p>
<p>The existing AMI that you’ll be building on top of is versioned, so you have a series of existing AMIs that all start with the prefix sample_ami_v{version}. You will also be following this naming guideline for your new AMI.</p>
<p>Versioning the AMI names with predictable prefixes allows you to filter them programmatically.</p>
<p>The nvtop apt package needs to be added to the AMI.</p>
<p>The AMI needs to be available in the us-east-1 region primarily, but also in the ap-southeast-1 and ap-south-1 regions.</p>
<p>The AMIs should be accessible from a different AWS account with the account ID: 123412341234.</p>
<p>Breakdown</p>
<p>Your JSON template is used to tell Packer what to do. In our case, we need to create an AMI from an existing image and add a package to it.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
